The forests of Pandora have many dangers.
But the most dangerous
thing about Pandora is…
...that you may end
up loving him too much.
We sing the chords to remember.
Each pearl is a story of our life.
A jewel for the birth of our son.
Netay!
A jewel for our adopted daughter, Kiri, -
born from the avatar of Grace, -
and whose design
was a complete mystery.
A jewel for the first meeting with Eywa.
People say we live in Eywa, -
and Eywa lives in us.
The great mother takes
care of all her children.
Happiness is simple.
I think a toad like
me would find it.
The first time I met your
father, I tried to kill him.
Love at first sight.
Before I knew it, we had four.
We sent people from heaven
back to Earth, but some stayed here.
Scientists loyal to the Na'vi.
And then there was
Spider. He was trapped here.
Too young for a cryocapsule.
The war had taken his parents, so
he was brought up by the scientists.
He was like a stray
cat that kept running.
He and our children were inseparable.
For Neytiri, he would always
be a stranger. One of them.
He belongs among his own.
- I got it first!
- Why do you have to have?
I was a few years away from having
my tongue hammered into the tuber.
But now it comes naturally to me.
I hate you!
I hate you to no end, Lo'ak! Crazy face!
Wow, that's good.
Soon the firewood falls.
He immediately emerges
from the rocks. Here it is.
Like, take it.
Neteyam, the great fisherman. Good boy.
- It's a big crab.
- By the stones, as you said.
- What is his size?
- So big.
Time passes. Like a dream.
- Kiri.
- Come here, brother.
Smile, skxawng.
Happiness is simple.
It can be a date night without children.
It's just luck...
...that it can end abruptly.
A new star in the night sky.
It could only mean one thing.
Ships slow down.
The People of Heaven were back.
ONE YEAR LATER
Heart rate increases.
They will probably get there. Take it easy.
Good pupillary reaction.
Take it out there.
Colonel, can you hear me?
Please lie down.
Translated, edited & synced by
--- MARIB ---
- Stun him!
- Hurry up!
- Call the guards!
- Grab it!
Hold it! Calm down, Colonel!
It's me, Corporal Wainfleet!
Lyle? Is it you?
Yes, and Z Dog.
And Fike.
Let me go. I am completely calm.
It didn't matter.
Attention. Two minutes
to land on Pandora.
The umbilical cord is missing.
Oxygen absorption: 89.
In case you're in any doubt,
you're Colonel Miles Quaritch, -
just younger, taller,
bluer and less pretty.
In two hours, I will
attack the Na'vi fortress.
It was deemed desirable
that I make this backup.
And if you see it, that
means I put the hooves away.
Parker, what else can I say?
Just remind him how it works.
Your memories and personality
are sent back to Earth, -
where you are grown.
You will make them inculcate...
Is it me or is it you doing this?
The idea is to transfer the psyche of
the toughest extraterrestrial actors -
as Corporal
Wainfleet and signed -
for recombinant bodies.
You are a recombined soul
with my memories and my charm.
You won't be able to remember my
death because it hasn't happened yet.
And it won't either.
No matter what, you, as a clone
of me, will thirst for revenge, -
mostly about Jake Sully.
Remember that a Marine
can never be defeated.
You can kill us, but
we'll regroup in hell.
Semper fi.
Ground Force Now!
Take them here!
Two minutes, guys.
- We have to go, bro.
- Father is going to kill us.
Now don't be an asshole.
Lo'ak, come back!
The whole box should be included,
both magazines and fuze guides.
- Go brother!
- Lo'ak!
Take it. Take a gun, kid.
Lo'ak, you don't even
know how to use it.
Dad showed me this.
A combat helicopter!
Go brother!
Lo'ak, where are you? Netay!
Are you unharmed? Where is your brother
- The low.
- Hurry up!
Netay!
Oh no.
Sheep?
What the hell are you doing here?
Sorry.
Sorry dad.
We are no longer in Kansas.
We are on our way to Pandora.
I know you are all
asking the same question:
Is it Blue Monday?
The sins of the past have
made us reborn as our enemies.
We have their size,
their strength, their speed.
Added to our training,
it is a powerful cocktail.
- Do we have a mission?
- We have this.
Our mission is to find and kill
the leader of the Na'vi rebel army.
It is called "toruk makto".
Jake Sulley.
Attack attack! I got you!
Come on, Tuk.
I'm definitely faster when I'm blue.
And animals show me more respect.
- They don't see me as a person.
- Wait, are you human?
They arrive!
THE FORTRESS OF THE OMATIKAYAS
They arrive! Kiri! Spider!
The warriors are back! Has come!
Come with me.
- Mother!
- Boom, boom, boom.
Intensify.
You are scouts. You have to keep
an eye out for enemies. At a distance!
Sound familiar? Here I let you steal
a mission and then you disobeyed.
- Kiri, help the injured.
- My brother is also injured.
- Tuk, go with her.
- Father, I take full responsibility.
Yes, because you are the oldest
and you must behave accordingly.
- MaJake, your son is bleeding.
- It's okay, mother.
Come in and get patched up.
You must be aware that you
almost had your brother killed.
You are banned from flying for a month.
Look at the Ukrainians. All. And
wipe the wickedness from your face.
- Should I breathe on it?
- Give him this.
- I would use yalnabark.
- Oh. Who is tsahik here?
You are, grandma,
but yalnabark is better.
- It hurts less.
- Powerful warriors.
What is that?
Neteyam and Lo'ak are
trying to live up to you.
It's hard for them.
I know.
You are tough on them.
I am their father. It's my job.
We are not a platoon. We are a family.
I thought we lost him.
- Hi there.
- Hey, Spider.
- I'll knock you out.
- Just come.
Only avatars are allowed
here. To go for a walk.
- Blue stripes do not grow.
- I can still dismiss you.
- What a day.
- It was long.
Very funny. It's so clean there that you
can breathe the air of the earth for hours.
I can only inhale yours for ten seconds.
Yes, it's downright, monkey cat. For you.
- Hi Max.
- Hey, kids.
Hi Mom.
Maybe I'm getting cocky,
but I see real evidence -
on a systemic response
at the global level.
I can't...
I will not use the word "intelligence".
“Awareness” is probably a better word.
It's as if the whole biosphere of Pandora -
is conscious and able
to respond cognitively.
I can't say that.
Then they crucify me.
Who do you think made her eggs?
- It was guaranteed Norm.
- Absolutely.
- You don't deserve to live.
- Think about it.
He is constantly with her.
I wanted to kill myself.
I wanted to drink acid.
He's in all the recordings.
Look at the look he gives her.
I imagine their avatars
together in the woods…
All alone!
It's not always cool to
know who your father was.
Hole in it. I don't even remember him.
No, Spider...
Spider...
You are not him.
BRIDGE CITY
Inside the airport!
No stay! Go!
Masks removed.
Colonel, it's the general.
General Armore.
Nice to meet you, colonel.
I hear good things.
But a lot has changed since
your last visit here. Has come.
The new command center
has just been commissioned.
Installers can erect
a building in six days.
We have done more here in one
year than in the previous 30 years.
We are not here to operate a mine.
I have a much more important mission.
The earth is dying.
Our task is to tame the desert -
with the aim of making Pandora
the new home of humanity.
But before we can do that,
we must appease the savages.
Sully's quirks grew
bolder and more frequent.
His attacks are well executed. There
is good coordination between the troops.
They attack mines and pipelines
and sabotage our supply chain.
They attacked a magnetic
train two days ago.
- Do we know anything about Sully's base?
- Yes. Show me the mountains.
It is a cave system in
the Hallelujah Mountains.
But every time we send
troops there, we suffer losses.
It's like stinging a wasp's nest.
After ten minutes in their
airspace, they swarm around us.
Colonel, we believe your blue
team will be mistaken for natives -
and not trigger an immune reaction.
How to test this hypothesis?
Hard.
Tremendous.
- We are approaching enemy airspace.
- Received.
- Come on, monkey!
- Wait for me!
- Tuk, come on.
- Okay okay.
Why did you bring her?
The princess who honks. "I'm chatting.
You mustn't go to the battlefield.
I'll tell mom if you
don't take me."
Come on.
- How crazy!
- Is there a body?
Oh man.
Kiri? Kiri.
Kiri. Kir...
- Are you OK?
- I did it again, didn't I?
Yes you can.
Kiri!
- You have to see to come back.
- Has come.
What is that?
We have to be home before dark.
- Too big to be human.
- Avatars?
Maybe, but none of us.
- What are you doing?
- Follow leads.
Keep your back covered.
Secured.
Make a phone call.
Holy shit.
We shouldn't be here at all.
Dad gives you a no-fly
zone for the rest of your life.
We have to look into the matter.
Brother, that's where your
dad and my dad fought.
- It's your father's suit.
- Holy shit...
Lyle, check the data on the camera.
- It's dead, Colonel.
- U.S. too.
- I have to report it.
- We have so many problems.
- They're going Dog, it's Eagle Eye.
- Eagle Eye, step forward.
I spotted someone.
They look like avatars, -
but they carry camouflage
and assault rifles. There are six.
What is your position?
We are at the old cabin.
Who are we"?
Me, Spider, Kiri...
...and Tuk.
Now you listen very
well. Step back in silence.
- Hurry away. Understood?
- Yes. We are on the way.
Dad, I know a loophole.
- You're in so much trouble.
- Now stop it, Kiri.
It is immediately the eclipse.
- Put it down or I'll shoot!
- Come with me.
- Let it go!
- Right now!
Put it on, put it on.
Come here! On your knees!
Stop bragging.
- Visit them for weapons.
- Kiri!
Take it easy.
Shut up!
What do we have here?
Listen, colonel. Four fingers.
He's a half-breed.
Show me your fingers.
You are his, aren't you?
Yes, you are his.
Where is he?
Unfortunately I don't speak English -
with assholes.
Where is your father?
Should he be with?
Shut up!
- Kiri! No, don't do that!
- You don't touch her!
You must not hurt her.
- Stay still.
- What's your name, kid?
Socorro spider.
Miles?
Nobody calls me that.
It was hell. I assumed
you were sent back to Earth.
Children cannot tolerate cryo, clap hat.
What are we doing, boss?
Iron Sky, Blue 1 here.
- Blue 1, move forward.
- We are ready for collection.
- Get us here.
- Dragonfly starts collecting.
We are bringing in very valuable prisoners.
- Blue 1, we're on our way.
- Arrival in ten.
We count.
Lyle, pass me the sound on this one.
- She's Sully's wife.
- It's a wild animal.
Translated, edited & synced by
--- MARIB ---
Give it up, Quaritch.
- Sully.
- Stupid pig.
It's not over as
long as I breathe.
I was hoping you would say that.
- You stay with the Iranians.
- But I'm a warrior like you.
I will say no more.
Yes.
There is nothing after.
Should we save the remains?
Blue 1, we'll be there in three minutes.
Three minutes.
Cover our backs.
Shut up!
So clap!
Skirmish in the back!
Lo'ak!
Little shit!
- Tuk, come on!
- Race!
Come with me!
Covered!
Go on!
Is that you, Mrs. Sully?
I recognize your business card.
Walk freely, Mrs. Sully.
We two have unfinished business.
Demon! I will kill you
as many times as it takes.
You and the corporal have
been really diligent, haven't you?
You raised a litter of half-breeds.
Na'vier!
Run Run run!
How are you, kid? Follow me. Clear?
Now!
Go on!
- Run Run run!
- After them!
Spider?
- Spider!
- Kiri!
Come here!
The spider is over there!
- So we're ahead. We have ten minutes.
- Blue 1, return to collection point.
- Blue 1, step back.
- Return!
Back back! To take off!
Kiri, come on! Has come!
Run Run run!
- Are you hurt?
- No, I'm fine.
Tuk, are you hurt?
So the danger has passed.
Is everyone unharmed?
Tuk!
We did it.
Thank you, All courage is, thank you.
Where is the spider?
They took him away.
Calm down, honey. He's a cool boy.
It probably will.
We'll probably all get
through this together.
Before hell!
Let me out!
He has become like a savage.
He thinks he is one of them.
The Quaritch creature can wade
here without Eywa spotting it.
- Our house is here.
- This applies to our children.
You can't ask me that.
I cannot leave my
people. I'm not going to.
He is chasing us. He's after our family.
You can't ask me that. Children
only know the forest. Our home is here!
He had our children. He
had them under his knife.
My father gave me the
bow here when he was dying.
He told me to protect
people. You are Toruk Makto!
It will protect people. Quaritch
has Spider and he knows everything.
He can lead them right here.
If people hide us,
they will be killed.
Do you understand?
I have nothing. I have no plan.
But I can protect our family.
One thing I know.
Wherever we are, the
family is our fortress.
- Where's Jake Sully?
- I do not know!
- We know, you know.
Form an image in your mind.
Does it represent the floating mountains?
- Release me!
- He bristles against.
Dan a thought and we'll see.
- I do not know!
- I don't like it either.
- Which clans protect him?
- I have no idea!
The front patch is going absolutely crazy.
It won't stop until
you tell us where he is.
I don't know, assholes!
Let me try the personal angle.
He's not your son.
Calm, Tarzan, calm.
Are you calm?
You are cool, kid. The researchers
gave you the approximate file, -
but you didn't reveal anything.
I respect that.
Maybe you want that.
This is Colonel Miles Quaritch. Deceased.
The drop in service.
I am not him.
But I have his memories.
And they tell me, -
that he was not the
best father in the world.
But that's no excuse.
I am not your father.
Technically, we're not related.
But I can help you.
I can get you out of here.
I won't ask you to betray Jake Sully.
You would never do that. You are faithful.
And I admire loyalty.
Now take it.
Otherwise, I have to leave
you at the back of the pack.
My heart is heavy as stone.
Tarsem is young but wise.
It will become a strong olo'eyktan.
The leader must die...
...so that the leader can be born.
Toruk makto will disappear.
People will know for sure.
A father protects. This
is his purpose in life.
A life ends.
Another begins.
Oh, Tuk...
The Sea Clans inhabit a world
apart. Thousands of islands.
An unknown area where we
can disappear without a trace.
Aren't we there soon?
AWA'ATLU, A METKAYINA VILLAGE
Let him stay.
Follow me.
Tuk.
Behave well.
Take it easy.
What is that? Should it represent a tail?
It is then too small to swim with.
Wait, Rotxo and Ao'nung.
Hello.
Tonowari was the chief of the
Metkayina, the people of the reefs.
- I see you, Tonowari.
- Jake Sully.
He was known as a tough boss.
But it wasn't Tonowari
who worried me.
I see you, Ron al, the
tsahik of the metkayinas.
I see you, Ron Al.
- What do you expect from us, Jake Sully?
- We are looking for a trip...
- Uturu?
- Asylum for my family.
We are reef people. You are people of the
forest. Your skills cannot be used here.
- So we want to know yours, right?
- yes.
Their arms are slender.
Their tails are weak.
You will be slow in the water.
The kids aren't even real Na'vi.
Yes we are.
There's demon blood in them!
Look here.
I was born from the sky people
and now I'm na'vi. You can adapt.
We will adapt.
My husband was toruk makto.
He led the clans to
victory over the Sky People.
Do you call it a victory
to hide among strangers?
Eywa apparently turned his
back on you, you chose one.
You must support my companion. She has
traveled a long journey and is exhausted.
Toruk Makto is a powerful war hero.
All the Na'vi know his story.
But we Metkayina are not at war.
We can't let you take the war here.
I'm done with the war, okay?
I just want to protect my family.
We asked bad luck...
- Will we be fired?
- It will be fine.
Toruk Makto and his
family are staying with us.
Think of them as our brothers and
sisters. But they don't know the sea.
Therefore, they will be like newborn
babies taking their first breath.
Teach them our way of life so they
won't be ashamed of being useless.
- So what are you saying?
- Thank you.
Thank you.
My son Ao'nung and my daughter
Tsireya will guide your children.
- Why?
- It's been decided.
Come see our village.
This way.
Come on, Tuk.
It's right here.
This is your new home.
It depends.
That's cool, huh?
- Sully is, get up.
- There's a family reunion.
- On your knees.
- Kiri.
What?
I need you to behave in an
exemplary manner. I'm serious.
Learn fast, take your turn and
avoid creating trouble. Understood?
Yes.
I want to go home.
Oh, Tuk...
Tuk is our home now.
We will probably get there.
- As long as we take care of each other.
- What does dad always say?
Sully is a fussy person.
Yes, Sully is a maniac.
So say it with conviction.
- Sully is fussy.
Come on!
Swim with us.
- What's wrong with them?
- They're bad at diving.
Stop. They just have to learn it.
- Are you OK?
- You are swimming way too fast.
Breathe.
You are not good at diving. You're
probably better at swinging through trees.
- Stop that.
- We don't understand your sign language.
- I'll probably teach you that.
- Where did Kiri go?
- Where is she?
- Have you seen it?
Get on board, find a seat
and don't get in the way.
- Come on hurry up!
- The coolest.
Stop halfway, Karl Smart.
Listen. A transmitter is
integrated into the mask.
If you run away, I'll catch
you at zero point five -
and gives you an
old-school finish. Understood?
- Understood?
- Yes.
- Ready?
- Everything is ready.
Listen carefully. Jake
Sully went into hiding.
But we'll probably find
him and his mad lady.
To be able to do this, we must be na'vi.
Screw too full.
We must eat like the Na'vi, ride
like the Na'vi and think like the Na'vi.
And first of all, we have to speak Na'vi.
Do you call that talking Na'vi?
You sound like a three year old.
OK, smart eye.
You have just been promoted from
our monkey mascot to our interpreter.
It is an illusion. If you want to live
here, you have to know how to ride.
Carefully tie the ribbon.
Feel his breath. Feel its strength.
Wait here.
- Look at his legs.
- Hold on.
Are you all right, Wood Goblin?
This war walker is difficult to master.
Maybe you should start with an il...
No, this one.
Remember that when diving, it is
important to take the right position.
I can do it.
Yes like this.
Calm.
I already love it.
breathing…
...and exhale.
Imagine breathing in a flame.
You have to say your heart rate.
breathing.
Breathe all the way down here.
And exhale slowly.
Lo'ak, your heart is beating fast.
Try to concentrate.
Breathing…
...and exhale. Clear your mind.
You learn to breathe.
Come on, losers!
Leave me.
What is that?
The Na'vi children do it with bare fists.
- Did Sully do it the hard way?
- What do you think?
What are we doing?
It's going to be good.
Forward.
It's you and me, baby.
Did I say you have
to tie the beak first?
Oh thank you!
Forward!
Can you see them?
Come on, we have to move on.
To take off.
Yes exactly!
That's right, Colonel!
Whose turn is it then?
The being of water
has no beginning or end.
The sea is around you and within you.
The sea is your home
before you were born...
...and after your death.
Our hearts beat in the lap of the world.
Our breath burns in
the shadow of the abyss.
The sea gives and the sea takes.
Water binds everything together.
Life and death.
Darkness to light.
- I understood! Tsireya!
- You did it.
They let us breathe underwater.
What is she doing?
- No idea.
- She's just looking at the sand.
What did you say?
Are you some kind of deformity?
Are you a freak?
No.
Are you sure?
You are not a true na'vi.
Look at those hands. See.
Skrid, fish face.
- Another four-finger deformity.
- Look at his little baby tail.
- Leave us!
- It's not normal.
Look at his tail. This is very cute.
You heard her. Leave them alone.
Big brother...
Walk with you. Now.
Sensitive. And from now
on, please respect my sister.
Has come.
Goodbye!
They are perverts, the whole family.
- Lo'ak...
- Calm down bro.
Yes, my hand is weird.
I am a deformity.
But it can do something
cool. First, I tie it very tight.
As well...
It's called a stroke, weak.
You will never touch my sister again.
Stop!
Stop that!
It's too stupid!
Oh, my tail!
My ear! Let it go! He's ripping my ear off!
- What did I ask you?
- To avoid creating trouble.
- It was my fault.
- You don't have to take out the trash for him.
Ao'nung called Kiri a deformity.
Say sorry to Ao'nung.
He's the chief's son.
I don't care how, as long
as you make peace with him.
- What did the others look like?
- Worse.
- Good.
- Much worse.
Leave.
What's wrong?
Nothing. I'm doing well.
Why shouldn't I?
Why can't I be
like everyone else?
Kir...
What is the tree runner doing here?
Sorry, I hit you plenty of times.
Lets be friends.
Join us for a hunt outside the
reef. This is where the men hunt.
- I must not.
- I asked the wrong brother.
Let's do it.
Go on!
Stay tuned, forest troll!
WOODEN BREAD SLICERS
- You survived.
- It was great!
Come on, I know a good place.
Call the fish.
What a fool.
Guys?
Ao'nung!
It's not funny!
Holy shit.
You are a tulkun.
You saved my life. Thank you.
Thank you.
I have no idea what you said.
They hurt you.
I try to remove it.
Trust me.
Friends?
Yes we are friends.
Bridge!
I'm sorry.
What's the matter, honey?
Do you miss Spider?
Yes, but that's not the case.
OK. What is it then?
I can smell it, dad.
- Tag who?
- Eva.
I can hear his breathing.
I can hear his heart beating.
She is so close.
She is here...
...like a word that's right on the tongue.
I know you think I'm crazy.
You're not crazy, honey.
So what does Eywa's heartbeat sound like?
Powerful.
Tell him what you told me.
Do you like stargazing?
My father came from a star.
The one right there.
- Lo'ak!
- Now I'm on it.
We'll see each other again.
- The boy has been found!
- The Sully boy has been found!
Let me see you.
He is unharmed. It's just a few scratches.
Give me the strength not to
tear my eyes out on my son.
No. My son knew not
to take him off the reef.
The fault is his.
Ok.
No. It's not Ao'nung's
fault. It was my idea.
Ao'nung actually
tried to talk me out of it.
- Lo'ak.
- Sorry.
Go on.
I go.
- Is it true?
- But what did you have in mind?
You said yourself that I
should be friends with them.
I don't want to hear about it.
You have shamed the family.
- Can I leave now?
- Next time, I'll tie a knot in your tail.
- It's understood?
- Yes. Lima Charlie.
- Where have you been?
- You should keep an eye on your brother.
Sorry.
Why did you speak for me?
Because I know what it's
like to be a big disappointment.
I would have loved to be there.
The sea gave you a gift.
The tulkuns haven't arrived
yet and no tulkun swims alone.
This one did.
He was missing his only fin.
The one on the left was just a stump.
Payakan. This is Payakan.
- Who is Payakan?
- An unruly young bull.
He's an outcast and he's missing a fin.
- He was supposed to be a killer.
- He killed Na'vi and Tulkun.
- Far to the south.
- He's not a killer.
- You are lucky to have survived.
- Well, he saved my life.
- He is my friend.
- My little brother...
The mighty warrior who fought
a killer tulkun and survived.
You don't listen.
- I listen.
- Lo'ak, come back.
Payakan!
Happy to see you.
Why are you excluded? What happened?
It's too painful.
I trust you. You can trust me.
Oh, that sucks.
Translated, edited & synced by
--- MARIB ---
Faster!
So here we are.
The Vig des Ancêtres
is our holiest place.
Eclipse is the best
time to be here.
Here it is. The Spirit Tree.
My beautiful daughter.
Hi Mom.
It's nice to see you.
But you look worried.
Honey, it'll be fine.
- What's wrong?
- Why am I different?
What does the Al-Mother want from me?
Who was my father?
Oh, mine...
- Go on!
- Kiri!
Kiri!
- What's wrong?
- She had a seizure.
Is she breathing?
- Take her back to the village.
- Let's go!
- Happy to see you.
- Neteyam, keep them away.
- How is she?
- Still unconscious.
No bleeding, no breakage.
The lack of oxygen did
not damage the brain.
But there is interictal
activity in the frontal lobe.
She must have had a seizure.
We can eliminate toxins.
- I'm not needed here.
- You are tzahik.
- Delete remedies.
- Outside! You did nothing!
- Come on, let's take a break.
- Let me take the drop.
Tuktirey.
She said she could smell
Eywa and hear her heart beating.
- It's a typical frontal lobe epilepsy.
- Epilepsy?
We see visions and experience religious
ecstasy like the one she described.
The association with the
spirit tree must have triggered it.
Don't let her do that again.
Never?
Jake, if she has another
seizure underwater, she could die.
Kiri, you're awake.
Kiri, sweet child. My lovely daughter.
Try this one: "I see you."
I said it too.
No way. Ngaati.
OK, it's coming out the nose.
Chief, one of the patrols
picked up a gunship on radar.
- Where?
- Above the sea, 400 km to the north.
Hold.
The signal disappeared offshore.
But if you continue the route, you
will come across this archipelago.
There are hundreds of
islands with countless villages.
It's him. Give me vases and
I'll come home with his scalp.
- We will be airlifted.
- Captain.
- Stop the engines.
- Yes.
Are you Score by?
Are you the bad ass taking my ship?
It's me.
The target is the whole archipelago.
I've never been there. You
know the waters. Who lives here?
Mainly metkayinas, about 50 villages.
Who are you?
Ian Garvin, marine biologist.
If there are 100 villages,
we search them all.
I hunt tulkuns. This is what
we do. I have quotas to respect.
I'm polite the first time. So it's over.
If you can't avoid it, enter it.
- All men to their posts!
- Hello, no pills.
- Rudder wires, speed.
- Yes.
- What was that?
- What is going on?
The Tulkuns are back!
Our brothers and sisters are back!
Their endless cycle of wandering
had brought the Tulkuns home.
Kiri!
- Kiri, come!
- Tuk, leave me alone.
- What do you want?
- See!
Let's meet them.
There is my soul mate.
My sister, I see you.
I see you and I'm happy.
Your son is handsome.
Thank you. How is your little one?
My little one is strong.
I met a boy.
Now stories had to be told about
the time they had been apart.
About death and births.
About old friends and new love.
TA'UNUI VILLAGE
Keep calm.
We are looking for weapons,
radios, technical equipment.
On your knees! Can you see it here?
Shut up!
We know that this man resides
somewhere here on the islands. Is he here?
Our tribe lives in isolation.
The man in the photo comes from the forest.
- What's he saying?
- That the people of the forest never come here.
I don't buy it.
He must search in the forest
if he wants to find this man.
They do not know anything.
Shoot this animal.
What do you do?
Take it easy.
Are your ears working now?
Now you have seen what they can do.
Jake Sulley. Power of Toruk!
He does not know anything.
Kill her.
Stop! Stop!
Cut it out of cardboard for him. If he
doesn't expose Sully, we'll kill the tsahik.
No, I refuse. I don't
want to be part of that.
They do not know anything!
Do we really have to kill her?
You don't have to do this. What
you are doing here is so wrong!
Do not.
- Burn the huts.
- Set it on fire.
Set it all on fire!
- Forgive me. I did not know.
- You have to stop the madness!
- Forgive me.
- We slipped.
Do not touch me!
Go on. Sit down!
- What's wrong?
- The people of heaven.
They're looking for you down south. They
have a human boy with them who speaks Na'vi.
- Did they kill anyone?
- Not yet.
They threaten to do so, but no one
will reveal where you are. On my order.
We must cast out this demon.
Catch him and kill him.
We have to think about it.
If we attack Quaritch, they'll
follow us here with all their might.
So what do we do?
We are looking for toruk
makto! Did he come here?
- It's useless.
- They are silent as the grave.
If we continue, he will run
away. We have to attract it.
I'm finished. I have
quotas to respect.
Do you want to hunt? Then we hunt.
Well not here? There
are too many villages here.
No no no.
They don't understand the
community bond between the Tulkuns -
and the Havna'vi. It would
be like killing their family.
If we hunt here, the
savages will come after us.
Exactly. A definitely savage.
I know what you're feeling.
I also feel completely alone.
Tell me. Why were you expelled?
I'm sorry. It hurts me terribly.
It's OK.
You allowed it.
You allowed him to
bond with the outcast.
Tsireya... You disappoint me, my daughter.
And you are the son of a great warrior.
You are better than that.
Payakan saved my life.
They don't know him.
Sit.
Sit!
Listen to my words, my boy.
At the time of the first songs, the
tulkuns fought among themselves -
to gain ground and take revenge.
But they realized that
killing, justified or not, -
just leads to more murders.
It was therefore forbidden to kill.
This is the tulkun way of life.
Payakan is a killer and
therefore an outcast.
- Sorry, but you're wrong.
- Lo'ak, you speak olo'eyktan.
Well, that's good!
I know what I know.
So it's good.
I will take care of him.
The storm will probably dissipate.
Lo'ak, I saw something today.
I saw a forest boy chosen by a tulkun.
I am very proud of you.
It wasn't Payakan who
killed the boys. I saw it.
The demon ship killed his mother,
so he gathered the young bulls -
and the Reef Boys to attack
the ship, and they were all killed.
But people from heaven,
not from him. It's not a killer.
According to the law of the Tulkuns,
he is responsible for their death.
Will he have to pay for the rest of his
life? He knows what he did was wrong.
- We need to tell my father...
- No. My father is furious.
- Your father will understand.
- Nope. He does not understand anything.
The whole clan hates me. Demon
blood, stranger. That's all they see.
I see you.
You are the brother of a tulkun.
You are one of us now.
- Did you find the mother?
- And the calf. 4000 meters.
- Hull in the water!
- Yes. Carrier plan activated.
Submarine teams, two minutes!
Batten the hatches! Hurry up!
The crews to their boats!
Let's make some dates.
People, get off the ropes!
Boats in the water!
Go!
To take off!
Depth charges ready. Dude, dude, dude!
What are they doing?
These are echolocation
sensors with which they navigate.
They keep them afloat
so they don't go deaf.
Picadors, far from you!
They isolate the cow from the
herd using the sound cannon.
They go after the mother because the
calf is slow and she does not leave it.
- Are they resisting?
- No, they never raise a palm.
But they are sailing demons.
Submarine teams, go!
Cut.
- We have the lady.
- Target in sight. Harpoons ready.
Then we go.
We attack from below,
where their armor is cracked.
- Alright, that's all now.
- Really bring me closer.
- Hold it steady.
- Arm the eater.
- Armed.
- Fire the eater.
2 ready. Arm the eater. Guy!
- Perfect match.
- Pull the devil.
- Boo yaa!
- 3-6, you owe a bajer.
The bags sink it and
pull it to the surface.
Bring me closer! Very close. 30 meters.
Pomegranate Harpoon.
10 meters. Let me in all the way.
Keep the boat stable! Wait wait.
The line turns!
Keep your hat and ponytail on.
- Full power back!
- Yes.
Hold it!
She has a grenade harpoon in her chest,
but she continues to swim. Beautiful.
We can only access the gland from
below, so we drill through the palate -
and in the brain.
They are very intelligent.
Probably smarter than us.
- No smarter than me.
- Then the bar is set low.
I'm the one with the harpoon.
Oh yes.
- How do you know they're smarter than us?
- They have more neurons and nerve fibers.
They are not only smarter,
but also deeply emotional.
More spiritual.
The area here corresponds
to our emotional center, -
but is proportionally much larger.
They have music, philosophy, mathematics -
and a complex language.
- Alright, that's all now.
- Bring on the horrors.
- So it's the hops?
- Exactly. Amrita.
Unfortunately for them,
dirt can stop human aging.
Totally.
The most valuable raw
material known to mankind.
This little container is
worth about 80 million.
Vulture!
Don't do this. It's never funny.
Amrita funds everything
here on Pandora now.
- Even your research, Dr. G.
- That's why I drink.
Are you taking anything
else? Is the rest just wasted?
Empty the bags and let it flow.
No, leave the bags alone.
They need to know it was us.
I need extra payment
to serve as bait.
Her name is Ro'a.
She was my soul mate.
She composed songs.
She was very popular. We sang together.
She waited many breeding cycles to
have a calf. The clan cheered her on.
What's going on, Tonowari?
What happens?
My spiritual sister and her child were
murdered by the people of heaven.
The war has come to us. We knew
our tulkun family was being hunted, -
but it happened far from here.
Now it is happening!
You must understand how
the people of heaven think.
- They don't care about the balance of life.
- They can execute us!
Now listen to him.
This is just the beginning.
Tell the Tulkuns to flee.
Say they have to run away.
Escape?
You have lived among us,
but you have learned nothing.
We will fight for our brothers and sisters!
No no no.
If you attack them,
they will eliminate you.
They will destroy everything you hold dear.
Listen to my words! Listen to my words!
Keep calm!
Now listen to my
father. He tells the truth.
Tell the tulkuns, -
that if they are hit by such a
person, they are destined to die.
Call me and I'll shut him up.
Saving their lives is the
only thing that matters, isn't it?
To save your family.
Notify the interpreters.
Off, off.
We must resume the fight.
MaJake... I won't stay here.
They just want us to strike again.
They don't hunt tulkuns. They hunt us.
- You're not going anywhere, little brother.
- I have to warn Payakan.
Zero. You stay here, skxawng.
He is an outcast. No
one else will tell him.
Brother, why do you have
to make everything so hard?
You mean why can't I be perfect
like you? The perfect soldier.
I'm not you, okay?
I am not you. He
is my brother. I do.
Is he your brother? No, I'm your brother.
Lo'ak!
Leave me.
Lo'ak! He wants to go to Payakan.
To come back!
- There's Lo'ak.
- Lo'ak!
- He wants to find Payakan.
- Wait for us.
Hold.
All men at their posts.
Come on, there's money to be won!
Payakan! Brother!
Lo'ak!
- Lo'ak!
- Expect!
What's wrong?
Shit!
Take it easy. I take it off.
Lo'ak!
Brother, help me! The boat is approaching!
Go on!
Go brother.
Summon the father! Just do it!
- Just do it!
- They will However, do you hear me?
- Did you see where they went?
- Outside the reef.
- Lo'ak?
- Sheep!
We are with a tulkun
who is attacked by a ship.
- It's 2 km away.
- Who is with you?
All of us, at the Trois Frères cliffs.
Hide and don't attack.
It's understood? We are on the way.
- Yes.
- It's getting closer!
Shoot!
Children are attacked. They defend
a tulkun. Your children are there too.
- The demon ship?
- Yes!
To arms! Sound the alarm!
- You better stay.
- I roll!
Submarines, batten down
the hatches! Two minutes!
- Ao'nung!
- Hurry up brother!
Rapidly!
Stop!
All at the same time!
It was hell. Sully's children.
- To take off. Not you.
- Sit down!
700 meters. The signal is clear.
- Go back up!
- Shoot!
- It's out!
- Come on, Tuk.
Go away! The
path! I attract them!
Payakan, dive!
Tuk, wait.
- 300 meters.
- Depth charges ready.
Dude, dude, dude!
No bombs. Children are
worth nothing if they are dead.
The waiting fire.
Circle them. Launch the submarines.
Subs in the tub!
Crabs, turn right.
- They must not escape.
- Wings in!
Such!
Pull the devil.
Where is Tuk?
Tuk!
Target in sight.
- It happens!
- We have to leave.
Change network. Guy.
Wait!
- You must beware! Move your hand!
- Hurry up!
To come back!
- Drop your weapon!
- Put the!
Stay here.
Come here, kid!
Put down your weapon!
- Put the!
- Drop the knife!
Hi, stop! You must not hurt them!
Stay still!
- Brother, are you okay?
- I've never felt better.
Return to the bridge.
Make sure he stays there!
I am on my way.
I remember you well.
Chain them to the railing.
Go on!
- Watch out, they bite.
- On your knees.
Come with your hand.
And then the other.
Be brave.
Na'vier!
- Wait!
- Left flank!
Stop! Stop them!
It's Sully.
300 meters.
They have our children.
Your daughter, Tuk, Lo'ak...
Jake, tell your friends to back off.
If you want your children,
you will show up alone.
You know you don't
doubt my composure.
I took you under my wing,
Jake, and you betrayed me.
You killed your comrades. I will
not hesitate to execute your son.
Now wait a bit.
Stay here.
They are performer killers.
They must die. Here today.
They are only after me. That's why they
hunted down the Tulkuns and took our children.
It's your fault! Your!
So I have to do it.
Offer expires soon.
What would it be?
Stop shooting. I'm coming.
MaJake, what's going on?
MaJake?
Be vigilant, everyone.
- To the point.
- If you shoot now, they will attack.
Wait until he's on board.
Payakan!
Shoot! Shoot!
Brother!
Take the tour! Turn me!
Set me on fire! Now now!
Get out, quick!
Set me on fire!
Duck!
Holy shit!
Give fire! Give fire!
Sully approaches. Keep an eye on him.
Come on, sit down!
So shoot something!
Stop!
After them!
Leak! Masks on!
Get him out!
Hurry up!
- Damage report?
- Bedrooms 2 and 3 are underwater.
Are you OK
- Harbor for the bow!
- Difficult to put in communication!
Set me on fire!
Now I have you!
- Get us for free!
- He's not reacting.
- Cut the cable!
- Who has the harpoon now?
Full power behind!
Leave the harpoon!
No cable, silly!
We are destroyed.
- We take water.
- Prepare your weapons!
- Otherwise, I thought you were so smart.
- Make up for the lack of food, Garvin.
Where have you gone, crafty Satan?
You probably think you're crafty, huh?
Duck!
- The pumps do not work.
- All men aboard!
Get him on a boat! Hurry up, guys!
- Neteyam!
- Do you need help, little brother?
Now clap and set us free.
- Get Tuk out of here.
- Hurry up!
Who is the mighty warrior?
Say it. Let's get out of here.
Lo'ak!
They have Spider. We have to save him.
Come on, we can't let him down.
Leave me!
Nope!
Ahh!
- Up with you, baby.
- I'm not your cunt, pig.
- We have to save her.
- Tuk, wait!
Sully is a fussy person.
Wait wait! Ready to go!
- Tighten the mask.
- Leave me alone.
Hurry up! It's an evacuation!
Tuk, that's not a good idea.
Cut here. Go on.
I got it.
We can still get there.
Now I'm attached again!
- Come on brother.
- Off.
Thanks guys.
Race! Go brother!
Run Run run!
Give me that.
- Run Run run!
- This way!
Covered!
Can you see them?
Bro, that was too crazy.
- To jump!
- Go on.
Your skxawng. I am hurt.
Shit! Give me a hand!
- Hold it!
- I got it.
- Take it.
- Holy shit.
- Hold it!
Go brother.
- Got you.
- Hurry up!
They have Kiri and Tuk.
I can't turn around.
Sheep! To help! It's Neteyam!
- Quick!
- Take it.
Neteyam is injured! Hurry up!
Shoot!
Watch his head.
Go on!
- Don't worry bro, we got you.
- Oh no.
Press it.
- Dad...
- I'm here.
I am with you, my boy.
I want to go home.
I know. We should probably go home.
- It will be fine.
- Sheep...
Neteyam?
No no no...
Netay!
Netay! No, all courage is...
My son! My son!
My son!
Can you hear me, Corporal?
I think you can.
I have your daughters.
Same offer as before.
You for them.
Where are your sisters
Where are they?
- I do not know.
- They're trapped aboard the ship.
They are at the moon pool.
On the well deck, amidships.
Come, I'll show you.
Answer me, Corporal. Spit it
out or there will be consequences.
I heard you.
Come on, we have to go. Go on.
Listen to me. Listen to me.
Listen to me. They have our daughters.
They have our daughters.
I need you to be with me
and I need you to be strong.
At present. Strong in heart.
Strong in heart.
Now we save our daughters.
- Stay with your brother.
- I want to go with you.
- You've done enough.
- Sheep...
The waiting fire.
Go on.
He is on his way.
I'm good. Go go!
Now we strangle it. That's why we are here.
- Stay with him.
- Nope!
Be vigilant, guys.
Now.
- Where are they?
- On the deck of the submarine.
There is a well in the middle.
They are at the railing.
No, stay here.
Talk to me, Corporal. The ship is sinking
and your daughters are sinking with it.
Your son didn't have
to die. It was your fault.
You thought you could protect
your family, but you can't.
There is only one solution.
Now let's get it over with
before we lose another youngster.
Covered!
- Who is affected?
- Zdinarsik?
Secured.
Prague, are you there?
Look for!
Forward!
To the left!
To the right. Surround her.
MaJake!
It's mom!
They are coming to kill you.
Sheep!
- Where is your sister?
- The path.
Stay behind me.
Kiri!
Time is running out, Corporal.
Do you really want to
lose another youngster?
You don't have to try!
Kill him, dad!
Kiri!
- Lower your weapons.
- You must not do this!
Keep them away.
Do it!
Nope...
- Put on handcuffs.
- Leave her alone.
Stay here! Don't come one step closer.
- Handcuffs!
- You stupid pig.
You don't have to do anything to him.
Drop it or I'll cut.
What is the kid doing to me?
It's not mine. We're not
even the same species.
You must not hurt
her. Let her go.
Now listen to me. Let her go.
- Mother, you must not kill him.
- A son for a son.
You must not hurt her.
- I cut.
- Now let her go.
Nope!
Kiri, Kiri...
- Spider!
- Get them out of here.
- Come with me.
- I owe you a death.
Mom, come on. Mother!
You don't spray, do you, Jake?
You know I never give up.
I will come and kill your whole family.
Sheep!
Come then.
Jack!
- The fire is coming!
- Back to the boat!
Stay by me.
Tuk!
Mother, take my hand!
Mother!
Come on, Kiri, we have to get out of here.
To climb up!
Come on Kiri. Race!
Bathing! Get in, Tuk!
Race!
- Mother!
- Run Run run!
Crawl on it!
I have you.
Give me your hand!
Open it!
- Open it!
- Back back!
Has come!
Tuk!
Up! Go on.
Crawl! Get up!
We guess! To continue!
Kiri, let's go!
This way!
Open it!
Mother!
Has come!
No, Tuk.
We can't go out!
- We'll stay together, okay?
- Yes.
All courage is, help us!
Kiri!
- Bridge!
- Mother and father are there.
- To input.
- I'm ready.
OK.
Jack!
Sheep?
Piss!
Come on, fool.
- Breathe, dad.
- Neteyam?
No, it's Lo'ak.
- Oh, Lo'ak...
- Sorry.
- Neteyam's death is my fault.
- Focus on the present.
The air pocket disappears. We
have to get out. Come on, dad.
- Can you find it from here?
- Yes, but it will be a long dive.
I can't handle it.
But you can. Hurry up.
I can't lose you too, dad.
Mom, I'm scared.
It will be fine. Stay
with me. Stay with mom.
It will be fine.
You just need to calm your
heart and be completely still.
Breathe from here.
The being of water
has no beginning or end.
The sea is around you and within you.
The sea is your home before
you are born and after you die.
The sea gives and the sea takes.
Water binds everything together.
Life and death.
Darkness and light.
- Hi.
- Kiri!
Everything will be fine, little sister.
Mom, I give you this.
It will help you.
Dad, you're fine.
Trust me. Say your heart.
Deep breathing.
Last breath.
Follow me.
Wait. Breathe.
Thank you.
I see you, my son.
MaJake!
Sheep! Sheep!
Has come. Come here.
- Tuk!
- Got you.
Brother.
Sully is a fussy person.
It was our greatest weakness -
and our great strength.
Thank you, Almoder. Thank you.
Let's get out of here.
My boy...
Come with me.
Spider!
Monkey!
Spider.
- Are you doing OK?
- Yes.
Come here.
A son for a son.
All singing strings have a final bead.
A father protects. This
is his purpose in life.
People say that all
energy is only borrowed.
One day it has to be returned.
Eywa takes care of all her children.
Nothing ever goes away.
Netay!
My family and I are leaving tomorrow.
Far from here.
Your son is with our ancestors.
You are metkayinas now.
That's how it happened.
We are now people of the sea.
It is our house.
Sheep! Look what I caught!
Wow, that's a big crab.
It was over there by
the rocks, as you said.
What's the matter, dad?
Why are you crying?
I'm just glad to see you.
I'm glad to see you too.
You try.
OK.
- Did you leave me some?
- Maybe.
Now look there.
Now I see it. I can't save
my family by running away.
This is our home, our fortress.
This is where we are.
Translated, edited & synced by
--- MARIB ---